♪〜
〜♪
（レガート･ブルーサマーズ）
ちょうど よかった
Oh, good.
Just who I wanted to see.
僕も君に会いたいと
思っていたんだよ
You don't like it, do you?
気に入らないんだね？
You don't like how I forced you
to shoot Nicholas D. Wolfwood dead.
僕が
ニコラス･Ｄ･ウルフウッドを—
君に撃ち殺させたことが
（チャペル･ザ･エバーグリーン）
ぐはっ
（骨が砕ける音）
（チャペル）ああっ うああ…
君の出番は終わったよ
Your scene is concluded.
Soon, the final curtain will rise.
もうすぐ最後の幕が上がる
（チャペル）うううっ…
（扉が開く音）
（ミッドバレイ）うん？
ああっ ああ…
Tell me one thing.
Why did you come here?
（ミリオンズ･ナイヴズ）
１つ聞く　なぜ ここに来た？
I... I don't know how
to live with a debt...
（チャペル）
か… 借りを作ったまま—
生きる方法は… 知らん
...that I h-haven't paid.
That's nonsense.
ナンセンスだ
Animals run instinctively
when they sense danger...
動物は 身の危険を感じると
本能的に逃げるというのに—
...but your behavior
is completely irrational.
君の行為は
全く理にかなってない
愚かと呼ぶにも値しない
Even the word 'foolish'
fails to describe you.
（チャペル）うう…
The only reason the human race
came to possess humanity and morals...
人間が—
ヒューマニズムやモラルなど
というものを持ったのは—
...was because they believed themselves
a superior breed of beast.
自分たちが優良種だという
誤った認識があるからにすぎない
絶対的な上位種の存在を知り
本物の恐怖を味わった瞬間—
The moment they taste the true fear
of knowing a far superior breed exists...
...humans act entirely on instinct.
人間は 本能だけで
行動するようになる
T-The cornered mouse
will attack the cat!
お… 追い詰められたネズミは
猫に襲いかかるぞ
That's because
the mouse is seeking death...
ネズミは 死を求めているのさ
...in order to escape the pain.
苦痛から解放されるために
あっ
This is the ravine
between life and death.
これが生と死のはざまだ
ぐあっ あああー！
あああーっ あう…
That's right.
That is your essence...
そう それが君の本質だ
...the essence of the animals
called Homo sapiens.
人間という動物の本質なのだ
ぐあああーっ！
消費するだけしか能のない
クズめ
Good-for-nothing
resource-consuming garbage.
フンッ
I know, my master.
分かっています
I will make Vash the Stampede
suffer eternal pain.
あの男に—
ヴァッシュ･ザ･スタンピードに
永遠の苦しみを
Hey, lady!
（ヴァッシュ･ザ･スタンピード）
オバちゃーん あっ…
Pardon me, MISS,
might I have some donuts?
おねえさん ドーナツ頂戴
Comin' right up!
How many will it be?
あいよ いくつにする？
$ $30 worth, please!
30ダブドル分
And make 'em fresh ones!
I don't want no day-olds.
あっ 揚げたてにしてよ
作り置きはなしだかんね
Yeah, yeah, I know!
はいはい 分かってますよ
（ヴァッシュの鼻歌）
Oof.
（ヴァッシュ）よっと
はあ ようやく
人のいる町に来られたよ
A populated city at last!
Oh, lucky day!
ラッキー ラッキー
Bonjour!
ボンジュール　んー いい香り
Ooh, that smells good!
This smells almost like honey.
まさにハニーって感じですな
これは
And without further ado...
…というわけで あぐっ
くあーっ うまうま
これ 激うま ハハッ
This is great!
This is super-tasty!
Oh, it's good to be alive!
生きてて よかったー アハハッ
Hey, wait for me!
（子どもＡ）待って 待ってよ
Mom says she's gonna buy each
of us a new toy! Hurry up!
（子どもＢ）
ママがオモチャ買ってくれる
ってんだぞ 早くしなきゃ
Have you been to Maggie's store?
She has some new bolts in.
（男Ａ）
マギーの店は ご存じですか？
新しい布が入ったそうですよ
Is that right?
I had no idea!
（女Ａ）まあ そうなんですか
知らなかったですわ
- Thanks a lot!
Is that right?
I had no idea!
（少年Ａ）
俺が手伝ってやるよ どの子だ？
I'll help you out.
Which girl is she?
（少年Ｂ）いいよ 自分で言うから
Never mind,
I'll tell her myself.
At least tell me her name!
（少年Ａ）名前ぐらい教えろよ
It takes three days to get there
by sand steamer. Forget it.
（男Ｂ）サンドスチームで
３日はかかるんだ やめとけって
It'll be fine! Trust me!
（女Ｂ）
大丈夫よ 私を信用してよ
（男Ｂ）君だから言ってんだよ
That's why I'm nervous.
（少女）
アハハッ… パパのカッコ変
You look funny, Daddy!
I'll get you for that!
（父親）言ったな コラ
（少女）ハハッ イヤ ハハハッ
- Eek!
- Watch where you're going, Linda!
（母親）リンダ 危ないわよ
（ヴァッシュ）うう… うっ
These are good.
うまいよな これ
These are really good.
ホント うまいよ
Why... are they so...
どうして こんなに…
（すすり泣き）
Mr. Vash!
（メリル･ストライフ）
ヴァッシュさん
Why do these huge incidents
happen around you?
どうして あなたの周りには—
こんな多くの事件が
起こるんですの？
Why did a nice person like
Mr. Wolfwood have to die?
どうして
ウルフウッドさんは…
あっ
Who is "he"?
“やつ”って誰のことですの？
- You heard about that?
- Please tell me!
（ヴァッシュ）聞いていたのか
教えてください
It's my fault. It's my fault
that everyone gets involved...
僕のせいだ
みんなを巻き込んだのも—
...that my friends die...
...everything.
友達が逝ったのも すべて
That's why you
can't be with me.
だから 一緒にいちゃいけない
That isn't an answer!
答えになってないわ
I need a real answer,
or I won't understand!
ちゃんと言ってくれないと
分からないじゃない
Please give it to me straight
in your own words!
お願いだから あなたの言葉で
ちゃんと教えて
As long as he's around,
I can never truly die...
やつがいるかぎり
死んでも死にきれない
ナイヴズがいるかぎり
...not as long as
Knives is around.
Knives?
ナイヴズ…
僕の兄弟だ
My brother.
That's why I should be alone.
僕は 一人でいるほうが
いいんだ
（ドアが開く音）
And besides, there's a girl
who needs you.
（ヴァッシュ）それに 君には—
そばにいてあげなきゃ
ならない子がいるだろ
That's...
（メリル）
そんな… そんなこと…
（ミリィ･トンプソン）
いいんですか？
Are you sure?
えっ
Don't you want
to follow him?
（ミリィ）
ヴァッシュさんを追わなくて
O-Oh, I'm glad that
no-good troublemaker is gone!
あ… あんな疫病神
いなくなって せいせいしますわ
We should report this quick,
and get taken off this detail.
早く会社に報告して
仕事から外してもらわなきゃ
We would need
more lives than...
命が いくつあっても…
I can handle it.
（ミリィ）私なら大丈夫です
でも…
But you...
If we don't go after him now,
we may never see him again!
今 追いかけないと—
ヴァッシュさんに 二度と
会えなくなるかもしれませんよ
Is that all right
with you, ma'am?
先輩は それでいいんですか？
フフッ 私は もう全然
へっちゃらヘの助ですから
I'm totally,
perfectly fine now!
And besides, if we don't work,
we won't get paid!
それに お仕事しなきゃ
お給料もらえないじゃないですか
ミリィ…
Milly...
Do you know
which way he went?
ヴァッシュさん
どっちに行ったか分かりますか？
Yes.
（メリル）ええ
Then there's nothing
to worry about.
なら 安心ですね
I'll be ready in a minute.
私も すぐ用意しますから—
Get your things
together, too, ma'am.
先輩も 荷物まとめてくださいね
Don't forget anything,
because we're not coming back.
忘れ物があっても
戻ってられませんよ
Yes...
That's true.
ええ そうね
Hey, this guy's crying!
（子どもＡ）
あっ この人 泣いてる
And he's a grown-up!
（子どもＢ）大人のくせに
Is there something wrong with that?
Everyone feels like crying sometimes.
（ヴァッシュ）いけないかい？
誰だって
泣きたいときぐらいあるさ
Why are you crying?
（子どもＡ）なんで泣いてんの？
A friend of mine
...went away.
友達がいなくなったんだ
- Why?
- Because...
（子どもＢ）どうして？
（ヴァッシュ）それは…
He died because of you.
（子どもＡ）
君のせいで死んだんだよね
はっ
ウルフウッドを殺したのは
君だよ
You're the one
who killed Wolfwood.
If you hadn't influenced him
with your foolish ideals...
君の愚かな考えに
振り回されなきゃ—
あんなことには
ならなかったはずさ
...he would not have
gotten himself killed.
君たち…
You...
あっ
ハッ
ああ… あっ…
あっ
I meant to pay my respects
for the death of our friend.
友人の死に対して 僕なりの
気を使ったつもりだけど—
Did I pass?
どうだったかな？
You...
貴様… 貴様！
YOU!!
抜くつもりかい？
Going to draw?
うっ
お願い やめてよ
Please stop!
Someone will die!
Someone else will die!
また死んじゃう
また誰かが死んじゃうよ
くっ…
That's right.
You can't possibly draw.
（レガート）そうだよ
抜けるはずがない
You seem to think
you've never killed anyone...
君は 自分が誰一人殺してないと
思ってるようだけど—
...but you're wrong.
それは間違った見解だよ
You merely think you haven't
because your hands aren't dirty.
自分の手が汚れてないから
そう思ってるだけさ
You believe it so strongly,
countless people are killed...
君は
その思い込みの激しい思想で—
何人も殺している
ガンホーガンズも—
...including the Gung-ho Guns
and Nicholas D. Wolfwood.
ニコラス･Ｄ･ウルフウッドも
You people forced me to!!!
お前らが
そう しむけたんだろうが！
Every time you make that expression,
my left arm shakes uncontrollably.
君が そういう顔をするたびに—
この左腕が
ブルブルと震えるんだ
My left arm...
君の手をつなげた—
...which holds your hand.
この左腕がね
なっ
（レガート）
僕は あの丘で待っている
I will be waiting
on that hill.
If you wish to shoot me now,
shoot.
今 撃ちたければ
撃ってもいいよ
H-Huh?
（子どもＡ）あっ あれ？
What happened to me?
どうしたんだろう 僕…
What happened?
（男Ａ）なんだ？ うっ うう…
ここまで…
ここまで もてあそぶのか—
Is this... Is this how far you
dare play with people's lives?
人の命を
You do the same.
（ミッドバレイ）
あんただって そうじゃないか
あっ
You destroyed July and Augusta,
and drilled a hole in the fifth moon.
ジュライとオーガスタを
ガレキに変え—
フィフスムーンに
大穴を開けた—
You're a monster.
“化け物”だよ あんた
You and he are the same breed.
お前は あの方と同類だ
Who are you?
何者(なにもん)だ？
I'm the eleventh
Gung-ho Gun...
（ミッドバレイ）
ガンホーガンズの11(イレブン)—
...Midvalley the Hornfreak,
the man who plays the greatest music...
ミッドバレイ･ザ･ホーンフリーク
最高の舞台で
最高の音楽を奏でる男
...on the greatest stage.
Will you join me
in a number...
（男Ｃ）
ヴァ… ヴァッシュ
１曲 つきあってもらおうか
ヴァッシュ･ザ･スタンピード
（男Ｄ）
ヴァッシュ･ザ･スタンピード！
...Vash the Stampede?
（町の人々の悲鳴）
- Vash?!
- Vash the Stampede!!
（町の人々）
逃げろ！ 助けてくれ！
（銃声）
（サックスの演奏）
（ヴァッシュ）
ぐあ… ぐあーっ
なんだ？
What?!
くっ
（ヴァッシュ）空間を伝う波長を
痛覚とシンクロさせているのか
Is he synchronizing
pain and airwaves?
（サックスの演奏）
うっ… うわあ！ くっ
（ミッドバレイ）
うーん 今日のシルビアは
すこぶる調子がいい
Sylvia is responding
very well today.
知っているか？
Did you know that, up close, the sound
produced by a famous instrument...
名器から放たれる音は—
近くで聞くと
案外 味気ないものだということを
...can actually sound rather flat?
Only you can enjoy
my greatest sound.
最高のサウンドを
堪能できるのは 君だけだ
A beautiful melody
deserves applause.
すばらしき音色には拍手
A splendid performance
deserves shouts of joy.
すばらしき演奏には
歓声をもって応えてほしい
Why don't you finish the job?
なぜ 手を抜く？
You could have killed me
easily by now!
本気になれば
いつでも やれるはずだ
The answer is simple.
I am under his orders.
簡単なことだ
あの方に命令されている
Knives...
ナイヴズ…
I can't defy him.
（ミッドバレイ）
逆らうことはできない
Those who serve him
have no free thought nor rights.
支配される側に
思想も人権もないのだから
You're wrong!
You have rights!
（ヴァッシュ）違う… それは違う
Is that the mercy
of a superior being?
それは
優良種としての慈悲か？
（男Ａ）
か… 体が か… 勝手に
l-I can't control myself!!
や… やめろ 行きたくない！
Stop it!
I don't want to go there!!!
Legato?
レガートか
フンッ
やめろ
Don't!
ぐあーっ
ぐっ…
（男Ｂ）イ… イヤだ
N-No!!
頼む 殺さないでくれ！ ああ…
Please, don't kill me!!!
くっ
ぐああーっ
Somebody stop me!!
誰か止めてくれ
Stop me!!!
止めてくれー！
（ヴァッシュ）
くっ ハア ハア…
ぐあああーっ
あっ ああ…
くっ ハア…
I should be alone.
（ヴァッシュ）
僕は 一人でいるほうが
いいんだ
Don't start brooding, ma'am.
（ミリィ）くよくよするの
なしですよ 先輩
You'll regret it.
でないと 後悔しちゃいますよ
You're right, you're right.
You're absolutely right!
ダメダメ ダメですわね
This is no time
to lose my nerve!
弱気なんか
こいてる場合じゃなくってよ
Go, Meryl, go!!
メリル ファイト！
（男Ｄ）うっ うう…
（ミリィ）あっ
（男Ｄ）うわあ うう…
Are you all right?!
（メリル）大丈夫ですか？
さあ 水を飲んで
Here, drink some water!
あっ ああ…
あっ…
（男たち）ああ…
ハア ハア ハア…
You have an iron will.
（ミッドバレイ）
まさに鉄の意思だな
う… うっ
Your single-mindedness
is commendable.
健気(けなげ)なまでの一途(いちず)さだ
あっ
But it's not over yet.
The show must go on.
だが まだだ ショーは続ける
（男たち）ひい…
Stop it!!
やめろ！
Don't struggle.
あがくなよ
ぐああ…
くっ…
（息が抜ける音）
（ミッドバレイ）あっ
ラが… ラの音が出ない
My 'la'!
I've lost my 'la'!!
The show's over.
ショーは終わりだ
You were trying for
a ricochet all along!
最初から
跳弾で狙っていたのか
フフッ だが—
But it's too soon
for the curtain call.
まだ カーテンコールが
残っている
なっ
This is my fate,
the fate of the dying.
これが滅びゆく者の…
私の運命だ
や… やめろ 今 撃つと…
Don't! If you shoot now...
やめろー！
Don't!!!
フッ
ああ…
くっ…
ううっ…
Legato.
レガート
Long, long ago...
（レガート）はるか昔—
... we should have died the instant
we fell upon this sandy land...
この砂だらけの星に
落ちた瞬間—
本当なら
死んでいたはずだったのに…
... without pain,
and without sorrow.
苦しむこともなく
悲しむこともなく…
The schedule has only
been set back a little.
今は 予定が
少し狂っただけにすぎない
The end is around the corner.
That is why I...
終わりの日は
すぐそこまで来ている
だから…
I...
クライマックスだよ
ヴァッシュ･ザ･スタン…
This is the climax,
Vash the Stampede...
（銃声）
ハア ハア ハア ハア…
Do you hate me?
僕が憎いかい？
I suppose you do. So many sad things
happened to you because of me.
そうだよね—
あんなに悲しいことが
いっぱいあったんだから
Be it friend or foe,
everyone you meet dies.
出会った人が
敵味方問わず死んでいく
It's enough to dry up
your tears forever.
涙も枯れ果ててしまうね
Shut up!!
（ヴァッシュ）黙れ！
But it isn't over yet.
でも まだ終わりじゃない
Did you think it
would end this easily?!
この程度で終われるはずないだろ
あっ ああ…
You are not human.
君は人間じゃない
I will teach you that
as a courtesy.
そのことを
レクチャーしてあげるよ
こ… この光は…
T-This light!
It is the power
you've always had.
君の持っている本来の力だよ
Actually, you could say
it is what you are.
いや 君そのものと言ってもいい
あっ ああ…
あああーっ
ぐっ…
ダ… ダメだ
N-No!
No!!
ダメだ
NO!!!
ダメだー！
あっ くっ… ハア…
Haven't you given up yet?
まだ固執するのかい？
That's annoying.
いらだたしいね
（銃声）
（ヴァッシュ）あっ くっ　ああっ
Y-You...
き… 貴様
You had better fight back
or you'll die.
反撃しないと死んでしまうよ
（銃声）
（ヴァッシュ）うっ…
フッ… それでいい
僕は かまわないよ
Go ahead.
It won't bother me.
An egotistical being like myself
can't be allowed to live.
こんな利己的で
不完全な存在が—
生きていていいわけ
ないじゃないか
Give me nothingness.
Give me death.
無を望むよ
死を望むよ
He is waiting. He is
looking forward to your visit.
あの方が待っている
君が来るのを
楽しみにしているんだ
I put on your left arm
because you aren't by his side.
君が あの方のそばに
いないから—
僕は この左腕を付けたんだよ
（銃声）
（ヴァッシュ）ぐっ…
Shoot me.
撃つんだ
I can't.
（ヴァッシュ）で… できない
Shoot me.
（レガート）撃つんだ
I CAN'T!
できないよ！
（ミリィの悲鳴）
ハッ
（ミリィ）うっ…
（メリル）ミリィ！
Milly!
（ヴァッシュ）あっ
（メリル）キャーッ
Stop!
Make them stop!
（ヴァッシュ）
やめろ… やめさせろ
（銃声）
（メリル）キャー！
Make them stop!!!
やめさせろー！
Then shoot me!
（レガート）なら 撃て！
ああ… ああ…
うう…
僕を撃つんだ
Shoot me.
あっ…
All you have to do now
is pull the trigger.
あとは 引き金を引くだけだ
If you kill me,
it will all end.
僕を殺せば すべてが終わる
Come now, choose
of your own free will.
さあ 選ぶんだ 自分の意思で
やめろ… 撃たせるな
Stop it...
Don't make me fire!
（メリルとミリィの悲鳴）
ああ…
Your faith in humanity
is as obstinate as it gets...
（レガート）
意固地(いこじ)なまでの信念だね
...to embrace every worthless ideal
that woman taught you.
くだらない理想しか並べない
女の戯言(ざれごと)を真に受けて
あっ
Maybe it's only reasonable since
you have lived for over 100 years...
100年以上も生きてきたから
しかたないかもしれない
でも それは… その生き方は—
...but that, your way of life
is nothing outside of comical.
滑稽以外の何者でもないよ
Rem Saverem...
レム･セイブレム
フッ 小憎らしい理屈を
並べただけの存在—
...a woman who could only pretend
her logic made sense.
A worthless human being...
くだらない人間—
...just like me,
but unlike you.
僕と同じだよ 君とは違う
SHUT UP!!!
言うなー！
Luck and persistence
won't work forever.
（ニコラス･Ｄ･ウルフウッド）
幸運やゴリ押しは
いつまでも通用せえへん
（銃声）
（ヴァッシュ）うっ…
As we journey,
we search and think...
（レム･セイブレム）みんなが
どうしたら幸せになるか—
その方法を探しながら
旅を続けているのよ
... of ways to make
everyone happy.
くっ…
Don't force your way
of life on others!
（ウルフウッド）
自分の生き方を強要すな
（レム）誰も人の命を奪う
権利なんてないわ
No one has the right
to take the life of another.
Don't tell me your dreams
in a world like this!!
（ウルフウッド）
こないな世界で 理想なんか語るな
Then if you turn around,
you will see the future.
振り向けば そこに未来があるわ
（メリルとミリィの悲鳴）
No!
あっ
I know, my master.
I will make him suffer.
（レガート）分かっています
あの男に—
I will make Vash the Stampede
suffer eternal pain.
ヴァッシュ･ザ･スタンピードに
永遠の苦しみを
（ナイヴズ）フフフッ…
アハハハッ…
♪〜
〜♪
（ヴァッシュ）夢を見たよ レム
I was dreaming, Rem.
Everything was so horribly dry
there, on that planet...
その星では 何もかもが
ひどく乾いていてね
... even people's hearts.
そう 人の心も…
As I watched the people
who lived there from far away...
僕は遠くから—
そこで生活する人たちを
見つめながら—
どうして
人は生き続けるんだろうって—
... I kept wondering
why they went on living.
何度も思うんだ
レム… 聞いて レム
Rem... Listen to me, Rem...
... I went wrong!
I went wrong!
僕は 間違ってしまった
僕は 間違ってしまったんだ
What should I do?
僕は どうすれば…